gaier adam





agaier





+49-15773666037

agaier.github.io



education

phd | computer science inria, university of lorraine (fr)| 2016-2020 (expected)

- research: design exploration, evolutionary computation, bayesian optimization
- advisors: Jean-Baptiste Mouret, Alexander Asteroth

msc | autonomous systems bonn-rhein-sieg university (de)| 2012-2019

 research: robotics, evolutionary optimization, neuroevolution, data-efficient optimization

msc | evolutionary and adaptive systems

university of sussex (uk)| 2011-2012

 research: biologically-inspired computation, insect intelligence, neuroevolution, hypernetworks

bsc | computer science

richmond american international university in london (uk)| 2002-2005

 research: species-conserving genetic algorithms for design

awards

- Best Paper Award 2018
 Genetic and Evolutionary
 Computation Conference
- Best Paper Award 2017 Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference
- Best Paper Award 2017 AIAA Multidisciplinary Analysis and Optimization Conference
- Drive-E Studienpreis 2015 National award for outstanding work in the electric mobility
- Pegge Scholarship 2011 High potential Evolutionary and Adaptive Systems student

overview

Nomadic American researcher with an eclectic background and research experience spanning evolutionary computation, robotics, and machine learning. Deep background in biologically-inspired computation, focused on neuroevolution, diversity, and novelty-based approaches. Concentrated on integration of evolutionary and ML techniques in doctoral research – applied to real-world design and control problems. Fascinated by of creativity, embodiment, and innateness in machine intelligence.

experience

google brain (tokyo, japan) 2019

| research intern

- developed methods to evolve weight agnostic neural networks (WANN) architectures which perform with random weights (weightagnostic.github.io/) %
- published tool for replication and continuation of WANN experiments
- published general-purpose neuroevolution tool %

inria (nancy, france)

| doctoral researcher

2015 - present

- developed approach to combine Bayesian optimization and quality-diversity techniques for design exploration in computationally expensive domains
- published source code of approach (Surrogate-Assisted Illumination) applied to aerodynamic optimization %
- improved data-efficiency of state-of-the-art neuroevolution algorithms by integrating machine learning techniques into the evolutionary process
- analyzed ability of quality-diversity techniques to tackle problems in highly deceptive objective spaces

bonn-rhein-sieg university (bonn, germany) | research associate 2012 - present

- developed techniques for aerodynamic design optimization and exploration
- evolved neural network controllers for terrain-aware fuel efficient vehicle control
- designed and taught masters level courses on evolutionary computation

tsinghua international school (beijing, china) | cs department head 2009 - 2011

- created school-wide CS curriculum for new K-12 international school
- taught CS courses to 7th to 12th grade students of mixed language abilities

various (beijing, china) | bartender, poker player, restaurant manager 2006 - 2010

Worked as a bartender, sound engineer, and musician at underground rock venue D-22 while supporting myself playing poker. Managed the Kro's Nest, a pizza place with all Chinese staff, becoming marketing lead when the restaurant became a chain.

- learned Chinese as a bartender, musician, and restaurant manager
- developed grit, mental resilience, and self-management skills as a poker player
- honed graphic design skills creating ads as marketing lead of a restaurant chain